Agatha Christie - Death On The Nile
PART ONE
CHAPTER 1
Linnet Ridgeway!
"That's Her." said Mr. Burnaby, the landlord of the Three Crowns.
He nudged his companion.
The two men stared with round bucolic eyes and slightly open mouths.
A big scarlet Rolls-Royce had just stopped in front of the local post office.
A girl jumped out, a girl without a hat and wearing a frock that looked (but only looked) simple. A girl
with golden hair and straight autocratic features--a girl with a lovely shape--a girl such as was seldom
seen in MaltonunderWode.
With a quick imperative step she passed into the post office.
"That's her!'! said Mr. Burnaby again. And he went on in a low awed voice.
"Millions she's got .... Going to spend thousands on the place. Swimming pools there's going to be, and
Italian gardens and a ballroom and a half of the house pulled down and rebuilt . . ." "She'll bring money
into the town," said his friend.
He was a lean seedy-looking man. His tone was envious and grudging.
Mr. Burnaby agreed.
"Yes, it's a great thing for Malton-under-Wode. A great thing it is." Mr. Burnaby was complacent about
it. "Wake us all up proper," he added.
"Bit of a difference from Sir George," said the other.
"Ah, it was the 'orses did for him," said Mr. Burnaby indulgently. "Never 'ad no luck." "What did he get
for the place?" "A cool sixty thousand, so I've heard." The lean man whistled.
Mr. Burnaby went on triumphantly: "And they say she'll have spent another sixty thousand before she's
finished!" "Wicked!" said the lean man. "Where'd she get all that money from?" "America, so I've heard.
Her mother was the only daughter of one of those millionaire blokes. Quite like the pictures, isn't it?" The
girl came out of the post office and climbed into the car.
As she drove off the lean man followed her with his eyes.
He muttered: "It seems all wrong to me---her looking like that. Money and looks--it's too much! Ifa girl's
as rich as that she's no right to be a good-looker as well. And she is a good-looker... Got everything that
girl has. Doesn't seem fair..." 
"Among those supping at Chez Ma Tante I noticed beautiful Linnet Ridgeway. She was with the Hon.
Joanna Southwood, Lord Windlesham and Mr.
Toby Bryce. Miss Ridgeway, as everyone knows, is the daughter of Melhuish Ridgeway who married
Anna Hartz. She inherits from her grandfather, Leopold Hartz, an immense fortune. The lovely Linnet is
the sensation of the moment, and it is rumoured that an engagement may be announced shortly. Certainly
Lord Windlesham seemed very pris!"
The Hon. Joanna Southwood said: "Darling, I think it's going to be all perfectly marvellous!" She was
sitting in Linnet Ridgeway's bedroom at Wode Hall.
From the window the eye passed over the gardens to open country with blue shadows of woodlands.
"It's rather perfect, isn't it?" said Linnet.
She leaned her arms on the window-sill. Her face was eager, alive, dynamic.
Beside her, Joanna Southwood seemed, somehow, a little dim--a tall, thin young woman of
twenty-seven, with a long clever face and freakishly plucked eyebrows.
"And you've done so much in the time! Did you have lots of architects and things?" "Three." "What are
architects like? I don't think I've ever met any." "They were all right. I found them rather unpractical
sometimes." "Darling, you soon put that right! You are the most practical creature!" Joanna picked up a
string of pearls from the dressing-table.
"I suppose these are real, aren't they, Linnet?" "Of course." "I know it's 'of course' to you, my sweet, but
it wouldn't be to most people.
Heavily cultured or even Woolworth! Darling, they really are incredible, so exquisitely matched. They
must be worth the most fabulous sums!" "Rather vulgar, you think?" "No, not at all--just pure beauty.
What are they worth?" "About fifty thousand." "What a lovely lot of money! Aren't you afraid of having
them stolen?" "No, I always wear them--and anyway they're insured." "Let me wear them till dinner-time,
will you, darling? It would give me such a thrill." Linnet laughed.
"Of course, if you like." "You know, Linnet, I really do envy you. You've simply got everything..Here you
are at twenty, your own mistress, with any amount of money, looks, superb health. You've even got
brains! When are you twenty-one?" "Next June. I shall have a grand coming-of-age party in London."
"And then are you going to marry Charles Windlesham? All the dreadful little gossip writers are getting so
excited about it. And he really is frightfully devoted." Linnet shrugged her shoulders.
"I don't know. I don't really want to marry any one yet." "Darling, how right you are! It's never quite the
same afterwards, is it?"
The telephone shrilled and Linnet went to it.
"Yes? Yes?" The butler's voice answered her.
"Miss de Bellefort is on the line. Shall I put her through?" "Bellefort? Oh, of course, yes, put her through."
A click and a voice, an eager, soft, slightly breathless voice.
"Hallo, is that Miss Ridgeway? Linnet.t"
'Jackie darling.t I haven't heard anything "I know. It's awful. Linnet, I want to see "Darling, can't you
come down here? My "That's just what I want to do." "Well, jump into a train or a car." "Right, I will. A
frightfully dilapidated of you for ages and ages.t" you terribly." new toy. I'd love to show it to you."
two-seater. I bought it for fifteen pounds and some days it goes beautifully. But it has moods. If I haven't
arrived by tea-time you'll know it's had a mood. So long, my sweet." Linnet replaced the receiver. She
crossed back to Joanna.
"That's my oldest friend, Jacqueline de Bellefort. We were together at a convent in Paris. She's had the
most terribly bad luck. Her father was a French Count, her mother was American--a Southerner. The
father went off with some woman, and her mother lost all her money in the Wall Street crash. Jackie was
left absolutely broke. I don't know how she's managed to get along the last two years." Joanna was
polishing her deep blood-coloured nails with her friend's nail pad.
She leant back with her head on one side scrutinising the effect.
"Darling," she drawled, "won't that be rather tiresome? If any misfortunes happen to my friends I always
drop them at once.t It sounds heartless, but it saves such a lot of trouble later! They always want to
borrow money off you, or else they start a dress-making business and you have to get the most terrible
clothes from them. Or they paint lampshades, or do Batik scarves." "So if I lost all my money, you'd drop
me tomorrow?" "Yes, darling, I would. You can't say I'm not honest about it! I only like successful
people. And you'll find that's true of nearly everybody---only most people won't admit it. They just say
that 'really they can't put up with Mary or Emily or Pamela any more! Her troubles have made her so
bitter and peculiar, poor dear!'" "How beastly you are, Joanna!" "I'm only on the make, like every one
else." "I'm not on the make!" "For obvious reasons! You don't have to be sordid when good-looking,
middle-aged American trustees pay you over a vast allowance every quarter." "And you're wrong about
Jacqueline," said Linnet. "She's not a sponge. I've wanted to help her but she won't let me. She's as
proud as the devil." "What's she in such a hurry to see you for? I'll bet she wants something! You just
wait and see." "She sounded excited about something," admitted Linnet. "Jackie always did get frightfully
worked up over things. She once stuck a penknife into some one!" "Darling, how thrilling!"
"A boy who was teasing a dog. Jackie tried to get him to stop. He wouldn't.
She pulled him and shook him but he was much stronger than she was, and at last she whipped out a
penknife and plunged it right into him. There was the most awful row!"
"I should think so. It sounds most uncomfortable!"
Linnet's maid entered the room. With a murmured word of apology, she took down a dress from the
wardrobe and went out of the room with it.
"What's the matter with Marie?" asked Joanna. "She's been crying."
"Poor thing. You know I told you she wanted to marry a man who has a job in Egypt. She didn't know
much about him so I thought I'd better make sure he was all right. It turned out that he had a wife
already--and three children." "What a lot of enemies you must make, Linnet." "Enemies?" Linnet looked
surprised.
Joanna nodded and helped herself to a cigarette.
"Enemies, my sweet. You're so devastatingly efficient. And you're so frightfully good at doing the right
thing."
Linnet laughed.
"Why, I haven't got an enemy in the world!" il) Lord Windlesham sat under the cedar tree. His eyes
rested on the graceful proportions of Wode Hall. There was nothing to mar its old-world beauty, the new
buildings and additions were out of sight round the corner. It was a fair and peaceful sight bathed in the
autumn sunshine. Nevertheless, as he gazed, it was no longer Wode Hall that Charles Windlesham saw.
Instead, he seemed to see a more imposing Elizabethan mansion, a long sweep of park, a bleaker
background .... It was his own family seat, Charltonbury, and in the foreground stood a figurea girl's
figure with bright golden hair and an eager confident face . . . Linnet as mistress of Charltonbury!
He felt very hopeful. That refusal of hers had not been at all a definite refusal.
It had been little more than a plea for time. Well, he could afford to wait a little...
How amazingly suitable the whole thing was. It was certainly advisable that he should marry money, but
not such a matter of necessity that he could regard himself as forced to put his own feelings on one side.
And he loved Linnet. He would have wanted to marry her even if she had been practically penniless
instead of one of the richest girls in England. Only, fortunately, she was one of the richest girls in England
....
His mind played with attractive plans for the future. The Mastership of the Roxdale perhaps, the
restoration of the west wing, no need to let the Scotch shooting ....
Charles Windlesham dreamed in the sun.
It was four o'clock when the dilapidated little two-seater stopped with a sound of crunching gravel. A girl
got out of it--a small slender creature with a mop of dark hair. She ran up the steps and tugged at the
bell.
A few minutes later she was being ushered into the long stately drawing-room, and an ecclesiastical butler
was saying with the proper mournful intonation: "Miss de Bellefort." "Linnet!" "Jackie!" Windlesham
stood a little aside, watching sympathetically as this fiery little creature flung herself open-armed upon
Linnet.
"Lord Windlesham--Miss de Bellefort--my best friend." A pretty child, he thought--not really pretty but
decidedly attractive with her dark curly hair and her enormous eyes. He murmured a few tactful nothings
and then managed unobtrusively to leave the two friends together.
Jacqueline pouncedin a fashion that Linnet remembered as being characteristic of her.
"Windlesham? Windlesham? That's the man the papers always say you're going to marry! Are you,
Linnet? Are you?" Linnet murmured: "Perhaps." "Darling--I'm so glad! He looks nice." "Oh, don't make
up your mind about it--I haven't made up my own mind yet." "Of course not! Queens always proceed
with due deliberation to the choosing of a consort!" "Don't be ridiculous, Jackie." "But you are a queen,
Linnet! You always were. Sa MajestY, la reine Linette.
Linette la blonde! And I--I'm the queen's confidante! The trusted Maid of Honour." "What nonsense youtalk, Jackie, darling. Where have you been all this time?
You just disappear. And you never write." "I hate writing letters. Where have I been? Oh, about three
parts submerged, darling. In JOBS, you know. Grim jobs with grim women!" "Darling, I wish you'd---"
"Take the queen's bounty? Well, frankly darling, that's what I'm here for. No, not to borrow money. It's
not got to that yet! But I've come to ask a great big important favour!" "go on." "If you're going to marry
the Windlesham man you'll understand, perhaps." Linnet looked puzzled for a minute, then her face
cleared.
"Jackie, do you mean--"Yes, darling, I'm engaged!" "So that's it! I thought you were looking particularly
alive somehow. You · always do, of course, but even more than usual." "That's just what I feel like." "Tell
me all about him." "His name's Simon Doyle. He's big and square and incredibly simple and boyish and
utterly adorable! He's poor--got no money. He's what you call 'county' all right--but very impoverished
county--a younger son and all that. His people come from Devonshire. He loves country and country
things. And for the last five years he's been in the city in a stuffy office. And now they're cutting down and
he's out of a job. Linnet, I shall die if I can't marry him! I shall die! I shall die! I shall die... 1" "Don't be
ridiculous, Jaekie." "I shall die, I tell you! I'm crazy about him. He's crazy about me. We can't live without
each other." "Darling, you have got it badly!" "I know. It's awful, isn't it? This love business gets hold of
you and you can't do anything about it." She paused for a minute. Her dark eyes dilated, looked suddenly
tragic. She gave a little shiver.
"It's-even frightening sometimes! Simon and I were made for each other. I shall never care for any one
else. And you've got to help us, Linnet. I heard you'd bought this place and it put an idea into my head.
Listen, you'll have to have a land agent--perhaps two. I want you to give the job to Simon." "Oh!" Linnet
was startled.
Jacqueline rushed on.
"He's got all that sort of thing at his finger-tips. He knows all about estates--was brought up on one. And
he's got his business training too. Oh, Linnei, you will give him a job, won't you, for love of me? If.he
doesn't make good, sack him. But he will. And we can live in a little house and I shall see lots of you and
everything in the garden will be too, too divine." She got up.
"Say you will, Linnet. Say you will. Beautiful Linnet! Tall golden Linnet! My own very special Linnet! Say
you will." "Jackie--" "You will?" Linnet burst out laughing.
"Ridiculous Jackie! Bring along your young man and let me have a look at him and we'll talk it over."
Jackie darted at her, kissing her exuberanfiy: "Darling Linnet--you're a real friend! I ]new you were. You
wouldn't let me down--ever. You're just the loveliest thing in the world. Goodbye." "But, Jackie, you're
staying." "Me? No, I'm not. I'm going back to London and tomorrow I'll come back and bring Simon
and we'll settle it all up. You'll adore him. He really is a pet." "But can't you wait and just have tea?" "No,
I can't wait, Linnet. I'm too excited. I must get back and tell Simon. I know I'm mad, darling, but I can't
help it. Marriage will cure me, I expect. It always seems to have a very sobering effect on people." She
turned at the door, stood a moment, then rushed back for a last quick bird-like embrace.
"Dear Linnet--there's no one like you."
M. Gaston Blondin, the proprietor of that modish little restaurant Chez Ma Tante, was not a man who
delighted to honour many of his clientele. The rich, the beautiful, the notorious and the well-born might
wait in vain to be signalled out and paid special attention. Only in the rarest cases did M. Blondin, with
gracious condescension, greet a guest, accompany him to a privileged table, and exchange with himsuitable and apposite remarks.
On this particular night, M. Blondin had exercised his royal prerogative three times--once for a duchess,
once for a famous racing peer, and once for a little man of comical appearance with immense black
moustaches and who, a casual onlooker would have thought, could bestow no favour on Chez Ma Tante
by his presence there.
M. Blondin, however, was positively fulsome in his attentions.
Though clients had been told for the last half-hour that a table was not to be had, one now mysteriously
appeared, placed in a most favourable position. M.
Blondin conducted the client to it with every appearance of empressement.
"But, naturally, for you there is always a table, M. Poirot! How I wish that you would honour us oftener."
Hercule Poirot smiled, remembering that past incident wherein a dead body, a waiter, M. Blondin, and a
very lovely lady had played a part.
"You are too amiable, M. Blondin," he said.
"And you are alone, M. Poirot?" "Yes, I am alone." "Oh, well, Jules here will compose for you a little
meal that will be a poem--positively a poem! Women, however charming, have this disadvantage, they
distract the mind from food! You will enjoy your dinner, M. Poirot, I promise you that. Now, as to
wine---" A technical conversation ensued. Jules, the maitre d'htel, assisting.
Before departing, M. Blondin lingered a moment, lowering his voice confidentially.
"You have grave affairs on hand?" Poirot shook his head.
"I am, alas, a man of leisure," he said sadly. "I have made the economies in my time and I have now the
means to enjoy a life of idleness." "I envy you." "No, no, you would be unwise to do so. I can assure you,
it is not so gay as it sounds." He sighed. "How true is the saying that man was forced to invent work in
order to escape the strain of having to think." M. Blondin threw up his hands.
"But there is so much! There is travel!" "Yes, there is travel. Already I have done not so badly. This
winter I shall visit Egypt, I think. The climate, they say, is superbl One will escape from the fogs, the
greyness, the monotony of the constantly falling rain." "Ah! Egypt," breathed M. Blondin.
"One can even voyage there now, I believe, by train, escaping all sea travel except the Channel." "Ah, the
sea, it does not agree with you?" Hercule Poirot shook his head and shuddered slightly.
"I, too," said M. Blondin with sympathy. "Curious the effect it has upon the stomach." "But only upon
certain stomachs! There are people on whom the motion makes no impression whatever. They actually
enjoy it!" "An unfairness of the good God," said M. Blondin.
He shook his head sadly, and brooding on the impious thought, withdrew.
Smooth-footed, deft-handed waiters ministered to the table. Toast Melba, butter, an ice-pail, all the
adjuncts to a meal of quality.
The negro orchestra broke into an ecstasy of strange discordant noise. London danced. "Oh, he won't be. I can trust Jacqueline's taste."
Joanna murmured:
"Ah, but people don't run true to form in love affairs."
Linnet shook her head impatiently. Then she changed the subject. "I must go and see Mr. Pierce about
those plans." "Plans?"
"Yes, some dreadful insanitary old cottages. I'm having them pulled down and the people moved."
"How sanitary and public-spirited of you, darling."
"They'd have had to go anyway. Those cottages would have overlooked my new swimming pool."
"Do the people who live in them like going?"
"Most of them are delighted. One or two are being rather stupid about it--really tiresome, in fact. They
don't seem to realise how vastly improved their living conditions will be!"
"But you're being quite high-handed about it, I presume." "My dear Joanna, it's to their advantage really."
"Yes, dear, I'm sure it is. Compulsory benefit." Linnet frowned. Joanna laughed.
"Come now, you are a tyrant, admit it. A beneficent tyrant if you like!" "I'm not the least bit a tyrant." "But
you like your own way!" "Not especially."
"Linnet Ridgeway, you can look me in the face and tell me of any one occasion on which you've failed to
do exactly as you wanted?"
"Heaps of times."
"Oh, yes, 'heaps of times'--just like that--but no concrete example. And you simply can't think up one,
darling, however hard you try! The triumphal progress of Linnet Ridgeway in her golden car." Linnet said
sharply: "You think I'm selfish?"
"No--just irresistible. The combined effect of money and charm. Everything goes down before you what
you can't buy with cash you buy with a smile. Result:
Linnet Ridgeway, the Girl Who Has Everything." "Don't be ridiculous, Joanna?
"Well, haven't you got everything?"
"I suppose I have .... It sounds rather disgusting somehow!"
"Of course it's disgusting, darling! You'll probably get terribly bored and blas by and by. In the meantime
enjoy the triumphal progress in the golden car. Only I wonder, I really do wonder, what will happen
when you want to go down a street which has a board up saying No Thoroughfare.'
"Don't be idiotic, Joanna." As Lord Windlesham joined them Linnet said, turning to him. "Joanna is saying
the nastiest things to me." "All spite," said Joanna vaguely as she got up from her seat.
She made no apology for leaving them. She had caught the glint in Windlesham's eye.
He was silent for a minute or two. Then he went straight to the point.
"Have you come to a decision, Linnet?"
Linnet said slowly: "Am I being a brute? I suppose, if I'm not sure, I ought to say No--" He interrupted
her.
"Don't say it. You shall have time--as much time as you want. But I think, you know, we should be
happy together." "You see," Linnet's tone was apologetic, almost childish, "I'm enjoying myself so
much--especially with all this." She waved a hand. "I wanted to make Wode Hall into my real ideal of a
country house and I do think I've got it nice, don't you?" "It's beautiful. Beautifully planned. Everything
perfect. You're very clever, Linnet." He paused a minute and went on: "And you like Charltonbury, don't
you? Of course it wants modernising and all that--but you're so clever at that sort of thing. You'd enjoy
it." "Why, of course, Charltonbury's divine." She spoke with a ready enthusiasm, but inwardly she was
conscious of a sudden chill. An alien note had sounded, disturbing her complete satisfaction with life.
She did not analyse the feeling at the moment, but later, when Windlesham had gone into the house, she
tried to probe into the recesses of her mind.
Charltonbury--yes, that was it--she had resented the mention of Charlton-bury.
But why? Charltonbury was modestly famous. Windlesham's ancestors had held it since the time of
Elizabeth. To be mistress of Charltonbury was a position unsurpassed in society. Windlesham was one of
the most desirable partis in England.
Naturally he wouldn't take Wode seriously . It was not in any way to be compared with Charltonbury.
Ah, but Wode was hers! She had seen it, acquired it, rebuilt and redressed it, lavished money on it. It
was her own possession, her kingdom.
But in a sense it wouldn't count if she married Windlesham. What would they want with two country
places? And of the two naturally Wode Hall would be the one to be given up.
She, Linnet Ridgeway, wouldn't exist any longer. She would be Countess of Windlesham, bringing a fine
dowry to Charltonbury and its master. She would be queen consort, not queen any longer.
"I'm being ridiculous," said Linnet to herself.
But it was curious how she did hate the idea of abandoning Wode .
And wasn't there something else nagging at her?
Jackie's voice with that queer blurred note in it saying, "If I don't marry him I'll die.
I shall die. I shall die .... ' So positive, so earnest. Did she, Linnet, feel like that about Windlesham?
Assuredly she didn't. Perhaps she could never feel like that about any one. It must be--rather wonderful---to feel like that.
The sound of a car came through the open window.
Linnet shook herself impatiently. That must be Jackie and her young man. She'd go out and meet them.
She was standing in the open doorway as Jacqueline and Simon Doyle got out of the car.
"Linnet," Jackie ran to her. "This is Simon. Simon, here's Linnet. She's just the most wonderful person in
the world."
Linnet saw a tall broad-shouldered young man with very dark blue eyes, crisply curling brown hair, a
square chin and a boyish appealing simple smile . . .
She stretched out a hand. The hand that clasped hers was firm and warm ....
She liked the way he looked at her, the naive genuine admiration.
Jackie had told him she was wonderful and he clearly thought that she was wonderful ....
A warm sweet feeling of intoxication ran through her veins.
"Isn't this all lovely?" she said. "Come in, Simon, and let me welcome my new land agent properly."
And as she turned to lead the way she thought: "I'm frightfully--frightfully happy. I like Jackie's young man
I like him enormously .... " And then with a sudden pang: "Lucky Jackie .... " viii
Tim Allerton leant back in his wicker chair and yawned as he looked out over the sea. He shot a quick
sidelong glance at his mother.
Mrs.
Allerton was a good-looking white-haired woman of fifty. By imparting an expression of pinched severity
to her mouth every time she looked at her son, she sought to disguise the fact of her intense affection for
him. Even total strangers were seldom deceived by this device and Tim himself saw through it perfectly.
He said: "Do you really like Majorca, Mother?" "Well" Mrs. Allerton considered. "It's cheap." "And
cold," said Tim with a slight shiver.
He was a tall, thin young man with dark hair and a rather narrow chest. His mouth had a very sweet
expression, his eyes were sad and his chin was indecisive. He had long delicate hands.
Threatened by consumption some years ago, he had never displayed a really robust physique. He was
popularly supposed "to write," but it was understood among his friends that inquiries as to literary output
were not encouraged. "What are you thinking of, Tim?" Mrs. Allerton was alert. Her bright dark brown
eyes looked suspicious. Tim Allerton grinned at her. "I was thinking of Egypt." "Egypt?" Mrs. Allerton
sounded doubtful.
"Real warmth, darling. Lazy golden sands. The Nile. I'd like to go up the Nile, wouldn't you?" "Oh, I'd
like it." Her tone was dry. "But Egypt's expensive, my dear.
Not for those who have to count the pennies." Tim laughed. He rose, stretched himself. Suddenly helooked alive and eager. There was an excited note in his voice.
"The expense will be my affair. Yes, darling. A little flutter on the Stock Exchange. With thoroughly
satisfactory results. I heard this morning."
"This morning?" said Mrs. Allerton sharply. "You only had one letter and that--" She stopped and bit her
lip.
Tim looked momentarily undecided whether to be amused or annoyed.
Amusement gained the day.
"And that was from Joanna," he finished coolly. "Quite right, Mother. What a queen of detectives you'd
make! The famous Hercule Poirot would have to look to his laurels if you were about." Mrs. Allerton
looked rather cross.
"I just happened to see the handwriting--" "And knew it wasn't that of a stockbroker? Quite right. As a
matter of fact it was yesterday I heard from them. Poor Joanna's handwriting/s rather noticeable--
sprawls about all over the envelope like an inebriated spider." "What does Joanna say? Any news?" Mrs.
Allerton strove to make her voice sound casual and ordinary. The friendship between her son and his
second cousin, Joanna Southwood, always irritated her. Not, as she put it to herself, that there was
"anything in it." She was quite sure there wasn't. Tim had never manifested a sentimental interest in
Joanna, nor she in him. Their mutual attraction seemed to be founded on gossip and the possession of a
large number of friends and acquaintances in common.
They both liked people and discussing people. Joanna had an amusing if caustic tongue.
It was not because Mrs. Allerton feared that Tim might fall in love with Joanna that she found herself
alway becoming a little stiff in manner if Joanna were present or when letters from her arrived.
It was some other feeling hard to defineperhaps an unacknowledged jealousy in the unfeigned pleasure
Tim always seemed to take in Joanna's society.
He and his mother were such perfect companions that the sight of him absorbed and interested in another
woman always startled Mrs. Allerton slightly. She fancied, too, that her own presence on these occasions
set some barrier between the two members of the younger generation. Often she had come upon them
eagerly absorbed in some conversation, and at sight of her their talk had wavered, had seemed to include
her rather too purposefully and as in duty bound. Quite definitely, Mrs. Allerton did not like Joanna
Southwood. She thought her insincere, affected and essentially superficial. She found it very hard to
prevent herself saying so in unmeasured tones.
In answer to her question, Tim pulled the letter out of his pocket and glanced through it. It was quite a
long letter, his mother noted.
"Nothing much," he said. "The Devenishes are getting a divorce. Old Monty's been had up for being
drunk in charge of a car. Windlesham's gone to Canada.
Seems he was pretty badly hit when Linnet Ridgeway turned him down. She's definitely going to marry
this land agent person." "How extraordinary! Is he very dreadful?" "No, no, not at all. He's one of the
Devonshire Doyles. No money, of course--and he was actually engaged to one of Linnet's best friends.
Pretty thick, that." "I don't think it's at all nice," said Mrs. Allerton fiushing Tim flashed her a quick
