I have often recalled the morning when the first of the
anonymous letters came.
It arrived at breakfast and I turned it over in the idle way
one does when time goes slowly and every event must be
spun out to its full extent. It was, I saw, a local letter with a
typewritten address. I opened it before the two with London
postmarks, since one of them was clearly a bill, and on the
other I recognized the handwriting of one of my more tire-some
cousins.
It seems odd, now, to remember that Joanna and I were
more amused by the letter than anything else. We hadn't,
then, the faintest inkling of what was to come--the trail of
blood and violence and suspicion and fear.
One simply didn't associate that sort of thing with Lymstock.
I see that I have begun badly. I haven't explained Lymstock.
When I took a bad crash flying, I was afraid for a long time, in spite of soothing words from doctors and nurses, that I was
going to be condemned to lie on my back all my life. Then at
last they took me out of the plaster and I learned cautiously to
use my limbs, and finally Marcus Kent, my doctor, clapped
me on my back and told me that-everything was going to be
all right, but that I'd got to go and live in the country and lead
the life of a vegetable for at least six months.
"Go to some part of the world where you haven't any
friends. Get right away from things. Take an interest in local
politics, get excited about village gossip, absorb all the local
scandal. Small beer--that's the prescription for you. Absolute
rest and quiet."
Rest and quiet! It seems funny to think of that now.
And so Lymstock---and Little Furze.
Lymstock had been a place of importance at the time of the
Norman Conquest. In the twentieth century it was a place of
no importance whatsoever. It was three miles from a main
road--a little provincial market town with a sweep of moorland
rising above it. Little Furze was situated on the road
leading up to the moors. It was a prim, low, white house with
a sloping Victorian veranda painted a faded green.
My sister Joanna, as soon as she saw it, decided that it was
the ideal spot for a convalescent. Its owner matched the
house, a charming little old lady, quite incredibly Victorian,
who explained to Joanna that she would never have dreamed
of letting her house if "things had not been so different
nowadays--this terrible taxation."
So everything was settled, and the agreement signed, and in due course Joanna
and I arrived and settled in, while Miss
Emily Barton went into rooms in Lymstock kept by a former
parlormaid ("my faithful Florence") and we were looked al2ter by Miss Barton's present maid, Partridge, a grim but
efficient personage who was assisted by a daily "girl."
As soon as we had been given a few days to settle down,
Lymstock came solemnly to call. Everybody in Lymstock had
a label--"rather like happy families," as Joanna said. There
was Mr. Symmington the lawyer, thin and dry, with his
querulous bridge-playing wife. Dr. Griffith--the dark, melancholy
doctor--and his sister who was big and hearty. The
vicar, a scholarly absent-minded elderly man and his erratic
eager-faced wife. Rich dilettante Mr. Pye of Prior's End, and
finally Miss Emily Barton herself, the perfect spinster of
village tradition.
Joanna fingered the cards with something like awe. "I didn't
know," she said in an awestruck voice, "that people really called--with cards!"
"That," I told her, "is because you know nothing about the
country."
Joanna is very pretty and very gay, and she likes dancing
and cocktails and love affairs and rushing about in highpowered
cars. She is definitely and entirely urban.
"At any rate," said Joanna, "I look all right."
I studied her critically and was not able to agree.
Joanna was dressed (by Mirotin) for le sport. The effect
was quite charming, but a bit startling for Lymstock.
"No," I said. "You're all wrong. You ought to be wearing an
old faded tweed skirt with a nice cashmere jumper matching
it and perhaps a rather baggy cardigan coat, and you'd wear a
felt hat and thick stockings and old well-worn brogues. Your
face is all wrong, too," I added.
"What's wrong with that? I've got on my Country Tan
Make-Up No. 2."
"Exactly," I said. "If you lived here, you would have just a
3little powder to take the shine off the nose and you would
almost certainly be wearing all your eyebrows instead of only
a quarter of them."
Joanna laughed, and said that coming to the country was a
new experience and she was going to enjoy it.
"I'm afraid you'll be terribly bored," I said remorsefully.
"No, I shan't. I really was fed up with all my crowd, and
though you won't be sympathetic I really was very cut up
about Paul. It will take me a long time to get over it."
I was skeptical over this. Joanna's love affairs always run
the same course. She has a mad infatuation for some com-pletely
spineless young man who is a misunderstood genius.
She listens to his endless complaints and works to get him
recognition. Then, when he is ungrateful, she is deeply
wounded and says her heart is broken--until the next gloomy
young man comes along, which is usually about three weeks
later.
I did rot take Joanna's broken heart very seriously, but I
did see that living in the country was like a new game to my
attractive sister. She entered with zest into the pastime of
returning calls. We duly received invitations to tea and to
bridge, which we accepted, and issued invitations in our
turn.
To us, it was all novel and entertaining--a new game.
And, as I say, when the anonymous letter came, it struck
me, at first, as amusing too.
For a minute or two after opening the letter, I stared at it
uncomprehendingly. Printed words had been cut out and
pasted on a sheet of paper.
The letter, using terms of the coarsest character, expressed
the writer's opinion that Joanna and I were not brother and
sister. "Hullo," said Joanna. "What is it?"
"It's a particularly foul anonymous letter," I said.
I was still suffering from shock. Somehow one didn't expect
that kind of thing in the placid backwater of Lymstock.
Joanna at once displayed lively interest. "No? What does it
say?"
In novels, I have noticed, anonymous letters of a foul and
disgusting character are never shown, if possible, to women.
It is implied that women must at all cost be shielded from the
shock it might give their delicate laervous systems.
I am sorry to say it never occurred to me not to show the
letter to Joanna. I handed it to her at once.
She vindicated my belief in her toughness by displaying no
emotion but that of amusement. "What an awful bit of dirt!
I've always heard about anonymous letters, but I've never
seen one before. Are they always like this?"
"I can't tell you," I said. "It's my first experience, too."
Joanna began to giggle. "You must have been right about my
make-up, Jerry. I suppose they think I just must be an abandoned
female!"
"That," I said, "coupled with the fact that our father was a
tall, dark, lantern-jawed man and our mother a fair-haired blue-eyed little
creature, and that I take after him and you
take after her."
Joanna nodded thoughtfully. "des, we're not a bit alike.
Nobody would take us for brother and sister."
"Somebody certainly hasn't," I said with feeling.
Joanna said she thought it was rightfully funny. She dangled
the letter thoughtfully by one corner and asked what we
were to do with it.
"The correct procedure, I believe," I said, "is to drop it into
the fire with a sharp exclamation if disgust." I suited the action to the word, and Joanna applauded.
"You did that beautifully," she said. "You ought to have been
on the stage. It's lucky we still have fires, isn't it?"
"The waste-paper basket would have been much less
dramatic," I agreed. "I could, of course, have set light to it
with a match and slowly watched it burn-or watched it
slowly burn."
"Things never burn when you want them to," said Joanna.
"They go out. You'd probably have had to strike match after
match."
She got up and went toward the window. Then, standing
there, she turned her head sharply. "I wonder," she said,
"who wrote it?"
"We're never likely to know," I said.
"No--I suppose not." She was silent a moment, and then
said: "I don't know when I come to think of it that it is so
funny after all. You know, I thought they--they liked us down
here."
"So they do," I said. "This is just some half-crazy brain on
the borderline."
"I suppose so. Ugh---nasty!"
As she went out into the sunshine I thought to myself as I
smoked my after-breakfast cigarette that she was quite right.
It was nasty. Someone resented our coming here--someone
resented Joanna's bright young sophisticated beauty--someone
wanted to hurt. To take it with a laugh was perhaps the best
way--but deep down it wasn't funny.
Dr. Griffith came that morning. I had fixed up for him to
give me a weekly overhaul. I liked Owen Griffith. He was
dark, ungainly, with awkward ways of moving and deft, very
gentle hands. He had a jerky way of talking and was rather
shy. He reported progress to be encouraging. Then he added,
"You're feeling all right, aren't you? Is it my fancy, or are you
a bit under the weather this morning?"
"Not really," I said. "A particularly scurrilous anonymous
letter arrived with the morning coffee, and it's left rather a
nasty taste in the mouth."
He dropped his bag on the floor. His thin dark face was
excited. "Do you mean to say that you've had one of them?"
I was interested. "They've been going about, then?"
"Yes. For some time."
"Oh," I said. "I see. I was under the impression that our
presence as strangers was resented here."
"No, no, it's nothing to do with that. It's just--" He paused
and then asked, "What did it say? At least"--he turned suddenly
red and embarrassed--"perhaps I oughtn't to ask?"
"I'll tell you with pleasure," I said. "It just said that the
fancy tart I'd brought down with me wasn't my sister--not
'alf! And that, I may say, is a shortened version."
His dark face flushed angrily. "How damnable! Your sister
didn't--she's not upset, I hope?"
"Joanna," I said, "looks a little like the angel off the top of
the Christmas tree, but she's eminently modern and quite
tough. She found it highly entertaining. Such things haven't
come her way before."
"I should hope not, indeed," said Griffith warmly.
"And anyway," I said firmly, "that's the best way to take it,
I think. As something utterly ridiculous."
"Yes," said Owen Griffith, "only--"
He stopped, and I chimed in quickly. "Quite so," I said.
"Only is the word!"
"The trouble is," he said, "that this sort of thing, once it
starts, grows." "So I should imagine."
"It's pathological, of course."
I nodded. "Any idea who's behind it?" I asked.
"No, I wish I had. You see, the anonymous letter pest arises
from one of two causes. Either it's particular--directed at one
person or set of people, that is to say it's motivated, it's
someone who's got a definite grudge (or thinks he has) and
who chooses a particularly nasty and underhand way of work-ing
it off. It's mean and disgusting but it's not necessarily
crazy, and it's usually fairly easy to trace the writer--a dis-charged
servant, a jealous woman, and so on. But if it's general,
and not particular, then it's more serious.
"The letters are sent indiscriminately and serve the pur-pose
of working off some frustration in the writer's mind. As
I say, it's definitely pathological. And the craze grows. In the
end, of course, you track down the person in question--(it's
often someone extremely unlikely) and that's that. There was
a bad outburst of that kind over the other side of the county
last year--turned out to be the head of the millinery depart-ment
in a big draper's establishment. Quiet, refined woman--had
been there for years.
"I remember something of the same kind in my last prac-tice
up north. But that turned out to be purely personal spite.
Still, as I say, I've seen something of this kind of thing, and,
quite frankly, it frightens me!"
"Has it been going on long?" I asked.
"I don't think so. Hard to say, of course, because people
who get these letters don't go round advertising the fact. They put them in the fire."
He paused.
"I've had one myself. Symmington, the solicitor, he's hadone. And one or two of my poorer patients have told me about
them."
"All much the same sort of thing?"
"Oh, yes. A definite harping on the sex theme. That's
always a feature." He grinned. "Symmington was accused of
illicit relations with his lady clerk--poor old Miss Ginch,
who's forty at least, with pince-nez and teeth like a rabbit.
Symmington took it straight to the police. My letters accused
me of violating professional decorum with my lady patients,
stressing the details. They're all quite childish and absurd,
but horribly venomous." His face changed, grew grave. "But
all the same, I'm afraid. These things can be dangerous, you
know."
"I suppose they can."
"You see," he said, "crude, childish-spite though it is,
sooner or later one of these letters will hit the mark. And then,
God knows what may happen! I'm afraid, too, of the effect
upon the slow, suspicious, uneducated mind. If they see a
thing written, they believe it's true. All sorts of complications
may arise."
"It was an illiterate sort of letter," I said thoughtfully,
"written by somebody practically illiterate, I should say."
"Was it?" said Owen and went away.
Thinking it over afterward, I found that "Was it?" rather
disturbing.
I am not going to pretend that the arrival of our anonymous
letter did not leave a nasty taste in the mouth. It did. At the
same time, it soon passed out of my mind. I did not, you see,
at that point, take it seriously. I think I remember saying to
myself that these things probably happen fairly often in out
of-the-way villages. Some hysterical woman with a taste fordramatizing herself was probably at the bottom of it. Anyway,
if the letters were as childish and silly as the one we had got,
they couldn't do much harm.
The next incident, if I may put it so, occurred about a week
later, when Partridge, her lips set tightly together, informed
me that Beatrice, the daily help, would not be coming today.
"I gather, sir," said Partridge, "that the girl has been upset."
I was not very sure what Partridge was implying, but I
diagnosed (wrongly) some stomach trouble to which Partridge
was too delicate to allude more directly. I said I was sorry and
hoped she would soon be better.
"The girl is perfectly well, sir," said Partridge. "She is
upset in her feelings."
"Oh," I said rather doubtfully.
"Owing," went on Partridge, "to a letter she has received.
Making, I understand, insinuations."
The grimness of Partridge's eye made me apprehensive
that the insinuations were concerned with me. Since I could
hardly have recognized Beatrice by sight if I had met her in
the town, so unaware of her had I been, I felt a not unnatural
annoyance. An invalid hobbling about on two sticks is hardly
cast for the role of deceiver of village girls,
I said irritably, "What nonsense!"
"My very words, sir, to the girl's mother," said Partridge.
"'Goings-on in this house,' I said to her, 'there never have
been and never will be while I am in charge. As to Beatrice,' I
said, 'girls are different nowadays, and as to goings-on else-where
I can say nothing.' But the truth is, sir, that Beatrice's
friend from the garage as she walks out with got one of them
nasty letters, too, and he isn't acting reasonable at all."
"I have never heard anything so preposterous in my life," I
said angrily. "It's my opinion, sir," said Partridge, "that we're well rid
of the girl. What I say is, she wouldn't take on so if there
wasn't something she didn't want found out. No smoke with-out
fire, that's what I say."
I had no idea how horribly tired I was going to get of that
particular phrase.
That morning, by way of adventure, I was to walk down to
the village. The sun was shining, the air was cool and crisp
with the sweetness of spring in it. I assembled my sticks and
started off, firmly refusing to permit Joanna to accompany
me.
It was arranged that she should pick me up with the car
and drive me back up the hill in time for lunch.
"That ought to give you time to pass the time of day with
everyone in Lymstock."
"I have no doubt," I said, "that I shall have seen anybody
who is anybody by then."
For morning in the High Street was a kind of rendezvous
for shoppers, when news was exchanged.
I did not, after all, walk down to the town unaccompanied.
I had gone about two hundred yards, when I heard a bicycle
bell behind me, then a scrunching of brakes, and then Megan
Hunter more or less fell off her machine at my feet.
"Hullo," she said breathlessly as she rose and dusted her-self
off.
I rather liked Megan and always felt oddly sorry for her.
She was Symmington the lawyer's stepdaughter, Mrs.
Symmington's daughter by a first marriage. Nobody talked
much about Mr. (or Captain) Hunter, and I gathered that he
was considered best forgotten. He was reported to have treated
Mrs. Symmington very badly. She had divorced him a year ortwo after the marriage. She was a woman with means of her
own and had settled down with her little daughter in Lymstock
"to forget," and had eventually married the only eligible
bachelor in the place, Richard Symmington.
There were two boys of the second marriage to whom their
parents were devoted, and I fancied that Megan sometimes
felt odd-man in the establishment. She certainly did not re-semble
her mother, who was a small anemic woman, fadedly
pretty, who talked in a thin melancholy voice of servant
difficulties and her health.
Megan was a tall awkward girl, and although she was actu-ally
twenty, she looked more like a schoolgirlish sixteen. She
had a shock of untidy brown hair, hazel-green eyes, a thin
bony face, and an unexpectedly charming one-sided smile.
Her clothes were drab and uaattractive and she usually had
on lisle-thread stockings with holes in them.
She looked, I decided this morning, much more like a horse
than a human being. In fact, she would have been a very nice
horse with a little grooming.
She spoke, as usual, in a kind of breathless rush:
"I've been up to the farm--you know, Lasher's--to see if
they'd got any duck eggs. They've got an awfully nice lot of
little pigs. Sweet! Do you like pigs? I do. I even like the
smell."
"Well-kept pigs shouldn't smell," I said.
"Shouldn't they? They all do around here. Are you walking
down to the town? I saw you were alone, so I thought I'd stop
and walk with you, only I stopped rather suddenly."
"You've torn your stocking," I said.
Megan looked rather ruefully at her right leg. "So I have.
But it's got two holes already, so it doesn't matter very much,
does it?" "Don't you ever mend your stockings, Megan?"
"Rather. When Mummie catches me. But she doesn't notice
awfully what I do--so it's lucky in a way, isn't it?"
"You don't seem to realize you're grown up," I said.
"You mean I ought to be more like your sister? All dolled
up?"
I rather resented this description of Joanna. "She looks
clean and tidy and pleasing to the eye," I said.
"She's awfully pretty," said Megan. "She isn't a bit like
you, is she? Why not?"
"Brothers and sisters aren't always alike."
"No. Of course I'm not very like Brian or Colin. And Brian
and Colin aren't like each other." She paused and said, "It's
very rum, isn't it?"
"What is ?"
Megan replied briefly:
"Families."
I said thoughtfully, "I suppose they are."
I wondered just what was passing in her mind. We walked
on in silence for a moment or two, then Megan said in a
rather shy voice, "You fly, don't you?"
"Yes."
"That's how you got hurt?"
"Yes, I crashed."
Megan said, "Nobody down here flies."
"No," I said, "I suppose not. Would you like to fly, Megan?"
"Me?" Megan seemed surprised. "Goodness, no. I should
be sick. I'm sick in a train even."
She paused and then asked with that directness which only
a child usually displays: "Will you get all right and be able to
fly again, or will you always be a bit of a crock?"
"My doctor says I shall be quite all right." "Yes, but is he the kind of man who tells lies?"
"I don't think so," I replied. "In fact, I'm quite sure of it. I
trust him."
"That's all right then. But a lot of people do tell lies."
I accepted this undeniable statement of fact in silence.
Megan said in a detached judicial kind of way, "I'm glad. I
was afraid you looked bad-tempered because you were crocked
up for life--but if it's just natural, it's different."
"I'm not bad-tempered," I said coldly.
"Well, irritable, then."
"I'm irritable because I'm in a hurry to get fit again--and
these things can't be hurried."
"Then why fuss ?"
I began to laugh. "My dear girl, aren't you ever in a hurry
for things to happen ?"
Megan considered the question. She said, "No. Why should
I be? There's nothing to be in a hurry about. Nothing ever
happens."
I was struck by something forlorn in the words. I said
gently, "What do you do with yourself down here?"
She shrugged her shoulders. "What is there to do?"
"Haven't you any hobbies? Don't you play games? Haven't
you got friends around about?"
"I'm stupid at games. There aren't many girls around here,
and the ones there are I don't like. They think I'm awful."
"Nonsense. Why should they?"
Megan shook her head.
We were now entering the High Street. Megan said sharply:
"Here's Miss Griffith coming. Hateful woman. She's
ways at me to join her foul Guides. I hate Guides. Why dress
up and go about in clumps and put badges on yourself forsomething you haven't really learned to do properly. I think
it's all rot."
On the whole I rather agreed with Megan. But Miss Griffith
had descended upon us before I could voice my assent.
The doctor's sister, who rejoiced in the singularly inappropriate
name of Aime, had all the positive assurance her
brother lacked, She was a handsome woman in a masculine
weather-beaten way, with a deep voice.
"Hullo, you two," she bayed at us. "Gorgeous morning, isn't
it? Megan, you're just the person I want to see. I want some
help. Addressing envelopes for the Conservative Association."
Megan muttered something elusive, propped up her bicycle
against the curb and dived in a purposeful way into the
International Stores.
"Extraordinary child," said Miss Griffith, looking after her.
"Bone lazy. Spends her time mooning about. Must be a great
trial to poor Mrs. Symmington. I know her mother's tried
more than once to get her to take up something--shorthand-typing,
you know, or cookery, or keeping Angora rabbits. She
needs an interest in life."
I thought that was probably true, but felt that in Megan's
place I should have withstood firmly any of Aime Griffith's
suggestions for the simple reason that her aggressive personality
would have put my back up.
"I don't believe in idleness," went on Miss Griffith. "And ·
certainly not for young people. It's not as though Megan was
pretty or attractive or anything like that. Sometimes I think
the girl's half-witted. A great disappointment to her mother.
The father, you know," she lowered her voice slightly, "was
definitely a wrong 'un. Afraid the child takes after him.
Painful for her mother. Oh, well, it takes all sorts to make a
world, that's what I say."
15"Fortunately," I responded.
Aime Griffith gave a "jolly" laugh.
"Yes, it wouldn't do if we were all made to one pattern. But
I don't like to see anyone not getting all he can out of life. I
enjoy life myself and I want everyone to enjoy it too. People
say to me you must be bored to death living down there in the
country all the year around. Not a bit of it, I say. I'm always
busy, always happy! There's always something going on in
the country. My time's taken up, what with my Guides, and
the Institute and various committees--to say nothing of looking
after Owen."
At this minute, Miss Griffith saw an acquaintance on the
other side of the street, and uttering a bay of recognition she
leaped across the road, leaving me free to pursue my course to
the bank.
I always found Miss Griffith rather overwhelming.
My business at the bank transacted satisfactorily, I went on
to the offices of Messrs. Galbraith, Galbraith and Symmington.
I don't know if there were any Galbraiths extant. I never saw
any. I was shown into Richard Symmington's inner office
which had the agreeable mustiness of a long-established legal firm.
Vast numbers of deed boxes labeled Lady Hope, Sir Everard
Carr, William ¥atesby-Hoares Esq., Deceased, etc., gave the
required atmosphere of decorous county families and legitimate,
long-established business.
Studying Mr. Symmington as he bent over the documents I
had brought, it occurred to me that if Mrs. Symmington had
encountered disaster in her first marriage, she had certainly
played safe in her second. Richard Symmington was the acme
of calm respectability, the sort of man who would never givehis wife a moment's anxiety. A long neck with a pronounced
Adam's apple, a slightly cadaverous face and a long thin nose.
A kindly man, no doubt, a good husband and father, but not
one to set the pulses madly racing.
Presently Mr. Symmington began to speak. He spoke clearly
and slowly, delivering himself of much good sense and shrewd
acumen. We settled the matter in hand and I rose to go,
remarking as I did so, "I walked down the hill with your
stepdaughter."
For a moment Mr. Symmington looked as though he did not
know who his stepdaughter was, then he smiled.
"Oh, yes, of course--Megan. She--er--has been back from
school some time. We're thinking about finding her something
to do--yes, to do. But, of course, she's very young still. And
backward for her age, so they say. Yes, so they tell me."
I went out. In the outer office was a very old man on a stool
writing slowly and laboriously, a small, cheeky-looking boy and
a middle-aged woman with frizzy hair and pince-nez who was typing with some
speed and dash.
If this was Miss Ginch I agreed with Owen Griffith that
tender passages between her and her employer were exceedingly
unlikely.
I went into the baker's and said my piece about the currant
loaf. It was received with the exclamations and incredulity
proper to the occasion, and a new currant loaf was thrust
upon me in replacement--"fresh from the oven this minute"
--as its indecent heat pressed against my chest proclaimed to
be no less than truth.
I came out of the shop and looked up and down the street,
hoping to see Joanna with the car. The walk had tired me a
good deal and it was awkward getting along with my sticks
and the currant loaf. But there was no sign of Joanna as yet.
Suddenly my eyes were held in glad and incredulous
surprise. Along the pavement toward me there came floating
a goddess. There is really no other word for it. The perfect
features, the crisply curling golden hair, the tall exquisitely
shaped body. And she walked like a goddess, without effort,
seeming to swim nearer and near. A glorious, an incredible, a
breath-taking girl!
In my intense excitement something had to go. What went
was the currant loaf. It slipped from my clutches. I made a
dive after it and lost my stick, which clattered to the pavement,
and I slipped and nearly fell myself.
It was the strong arm of the goddess that caught and held me.
I began to stammer: "Th-thanks awfully, I'm ff-frightfully
sorry."
She had retrieved the currant loaf and handed it to me
together with the stick. And then she smiled kindly and said
cheerfully, "Don't mention it. No trouble, I assure you," and
the magic died completely before the flat, competent voice.
A nice, healthy-looking, well set-up girl; no more.
I fell to reflecting what would have happened if the gods
had given Helen of Troy exactly those flat accents. How
strange that a girl could trouble your inmost soul so long as
she kept her mouth shut, and that the moment she spoke the
glamor could vanish as though it had never been.
I had known the reverse happen, though. I had seen a little
sad monkey-faced woman whom no one would turn to look at
twice. Then she had opened her mouth and suddenly enchantment
had lived and bloomed and Cleopatra had cast her spell
anew.
Joanna had drawn up at the curb beside me without my
