"You do see, don't you, that she's got to be killed?"
The question floated out into the still night air, seemed to hang there a moment and then drift away down into the darkness towards the Dead Sea.
Hercule Poirot paused a minute with his hand on the window catch. Frowning, he shut it decisively, thereby excluding any injurious night air! Hercule Poirot had been brought up to believe that all outside air was best left outside, and that night air was especially dangerous to the health.
As he pulled the curtains neatly over the window and walked to his bed, he smiled tolerantly to himself. "You do see, don't you, that she's got to be killed?" Curious words for one Hercule Poirot, detective, to overhear on his first night in Jerusalem.
"Decidedly, wherever I go, there is something to remind me of crime!" he murmured to himself. His smile continued as he remembered a story he had once heard concerning Anthony Trollope, the novelist.
Trollope was crossing the Atlantic at the time and had overheard two fellow passengers discussing the last published installment of one of his novels.
"Very good," one man had declared. "But he ought to kill off that tiresome old woman."
With a broad smile the novelist had addressed them: "Gentlemen, I am much obliged to you! I will go and kill her immediately!"
Hercule Poirot wondered what had occasioned the words he had just overheard. A collaboration, perhaps, over a play or a book. He thought, still smiling: "Those words might be remembered one day, and be given a more sinister meaning."
There had been, he now recollected, a curious nervous intensity in the voice-a tremor that spoke of some intense emotional strain. A man's voice-or a boy's . . .
Hercule Poirot thought to himself as he turned out the light by his bed: "I should know that voice again. . . ."
Their elbows on the windowsill, their heads close together, Raymond and Carol Boynton gazed out into the blue depths of the night. Nervously, Raymond repeated his former words: "You do see, don't you, that she's got to be killed?"
Carol Boynton stirred slightly. She said, her voice deep and hoarse: "It's horrible. . . ."
"It's not more horrible than this!"
"I suppose not. . . ."
Raymond said violently: "It can't go on like this-it can't. . . . We must do something. . . . And there isn't anything else we can do. . . ." Carol said-but her voice was unconvincing and she knew it: "If we could get away somehow . . . ?"
"We can't." His voice was empty and hopeless. "Carol, you know we can't . . ."
The girl shivered.
"I know Ray- I know."
He gave a sudden short bitter laugh. "People would say we were crazy-not to be able just to walk out-"Carol said slowly: "Perhaps we are crazy!"
"I daresay. Yes, I daresay we are. Anyway we soon shall be . . . I suppose some people would say we are already. Here we are calmly planning, in cold blood, to kill our own mother!"
Carol said sharply: "She isn't our own mother!"
"No, that's true."
There was a pause and then Raymond said, his voice now quietly matter-of-fact: "You do agree, Carol?"
Carol answered steadily: "I think she ought to die-yes . . ." Then she broke out suddenly: "She's mad . . . I'm quite sure she's mad . . . She-she couldn't torture us like she does if she were sane. For years we've been saying: 'This can't go on!' And it has gone on! We've said, 'She'll die sometime'-but she hasn't died! I don't think she ever will die unless-"
Raymond said steadily: "Unless we kill her . . ."
"Yes."
She clenched her hands on the windowsill in front of her.
Her brother went on in a cool matter-of-fact tone, with just a slight tremor denoting his deep underlying excitement: "You see why it's got to be one of us, don't you? With Lennox, there's Nadine to consider. And we couldn't bring Jinny into it."
Carol shivered. "Poor Jinny . . . I'm so afraid . . ."
"I know. It's getting pretty bad, isn't it? That's why something's got to be done quickly-before she goes right over the edge."
Carol stood up suddenly, pushing back the tumbled chestnut hair from her forehead. "Ray," she said. "You don't think it's really wrong, do you?"
He answered in that same would-be dispassionate tone: "No. I think it's just like killing a mad dog-something that's doing harm in the world and must be stopped. This is the only way of stopping it."
Carol murmured: "But they'd-they'd send us to the chair just the same . . . I mean we couldn't explain what she's like . . . It would sound fantastic . . . In a way, you know, it's all in our own minds!"
Raymond said: "Nobody will ever know. I've got a plan. I've thought it all out. We shall be quite safe."
Carol turned suddenly round on him. "Ray-somehow or other-you're different. Something's happened to you . . . What's put all this into your head?"
"Why should you think anything's 'happened' to me?" He turned his head away, staring out into the night.
"Because it has . . . Ray, was it that girl on the train?"
"No, of course not-why should it be? Oh, Carol, don't talk nonsense. Let's get back again to-to-"
"To your plan? Are you sure it's a good plan?"
"Yes. I think so . . . We must wait for the right opportunity, of course. And then-if it goes all right-we shall be free-all of us."
"Free?" Carol gave a little sigh. She looked up at the stars. Then suddenly she shook from head to foot in a sudden storm of weeping.
"Carol, what's the matter?" She sobbed out brokenly: "It's so lovely-the night and the blueness and the stars. If only we could be part of it all . . . If only we could be like other people instead of being as we are-all queer and warped and wrong."
"But we shall be all right when she's dead!"
"Are you sure? Isn't it too late? Shan't we always be queer and different?"
"No, no, no."
"I wonder-"
"Carol, if you'd rather not-"
She pushed his comforting arm aside. "No, I'm with you-definitely I'm with you! Because of the others-especially Jinny. We must save Jinny!"
Raymond paused a moment. "Then-we'll go on with it?"
"Yes!"
"Good. I'll tell you my plan . . ."
He bent his head to hers.
2
Miss Sarah King, M.B., stood by the table in the writing-room of the Solomon Hotel in Jerusalem idly turning over the papers and magazines. A frown contracted her brows and she looked preoccupied.
The tall, middle-aged Frenchman who entered the room from the hall watched her for a moment or two before strolling up to the opposite side of the table. When their eyes met, Sarah made a little gesture of smiling recognition.
She remembered that this man had come to her help when traveling from Cairo and had carried one of her suitcases at a moment when no porter appeared to be available.
"You like Jerusalem, yes?" asked Dr. Gerard, after they had exchanged greetings.
"It's rather terrible in some ways," said Sarah, and added: "Religion is very odd!"
The Frenchman looked amused. "I know what you mean." His English was very nearly perfect. "Every imaginable sect squabbling and fighting!"
"And the awful things they've built, too!" Said Sarah.
"Yes, indeed."
Sarah sighed. "They turned me out of one place today because I had on a sleeveless dress," she said ruefully. "Apparently the Almighty doesn't like my arms in spite of having made them."
Dr. Gerard laughed. Then he said: "I was about to order some coffee. You will join me, Miss-?"
"King, my name is. Sarah King."
"And mine-permit me." He whipped out a card.
Taking it, Sarah's eyes widened in delighted awe. "Dr. Theodore Gerard? Oh! I am excited to meet you. I've read all your works, of course. Your views on schizophrenia are frightfully interesting." "Of course?" Gerard's eyebrows rose inquisitively.
Sarah explained rather diffidently. "You see-I'm by way of being a doctor myself. Just got my M.B.."
"Ah! I see."
Dr. Gerard ordered coffee and they sat down in a corner of the lounge. The Frenchman was less interested in Sarah's medical achievements than in the black hair that rippled back from her forehead and the beautifully shaped red mouth. He was amused at the obvious awe with which she regarded him.
"You are staying here long?" he asked conversationally.
"A few days. That is all. Then I want to go to Petra."
"Aha? I, too, was thinking of going there if it does not take too long. You see, I have to be back in Paris on the 14th."
"It takes about a week, I believe. Two days to go, two days there and two days back again."
"I must go to the travel bureau in the morning and see what can be arranged."
A party of people entered the lounge and sat down.
Sarah watched them with some interest. She lowered her voice: "Those people who have just come in-did you notice them on the train the other night? They left Cairo the same time as we did."
Dr. Gerard screwed in an eyeglass and directed his glance across the room. "Americans?"
Sarah nodded.
"Yes. An American family. But-rather an unusual one, I think."
"Unusual? How unusual?"
"Well, look at them. Especially at the old woman." Dr. Gerard complied. His keen professional glance flitted swiftly from face to face. He noticed first a tall, rather loose-boned man-age about thirty. The face was pleasant but weak and his manner seemed oddly apathetic. Then there were two good-looking youngsters-the boy had almost a Greek head. "Something the matter with him, too," thought Dr. Gerard. "Yes-a definite state of nervous tension." The girl was clearly his sister, a strong resemblance, and she also was in an excitable condition. There was another girl younger still-with golden red hair that stood out like a halo; her hands were very restless; they were tearing and pulling at the handkerchief in her lap. Yet another woman, young, calm, dark-haired with a creamy pallor, a placid face not unlike a Luini Madonna. Nothing jumpy about her! And the center of the group-"Heavens!" thought Dr. Gerard, with a Frenchman's candid repulsion. "What a horror of a woman!" Old, swollen, bloated, sitting there immovable in the midst of them-a distorted old spider in the center of a web!
To Sarah he said: "La Manian, she is not beautiful, eh?" And he shrugged his shoulders.
"There's something rather-sinister about her, don't you think?" asked Sarah.
Dr. Gerard scrutinized her again. This time his eye was professional, not aesthetic. "Dropsy-cardiac-" He added a glib medical phrase.
"Oh, yes, that!" Sarah dismissed the medical side. "But there is something odd in their attitude to her, don't you think?"
"Who are they, do you know?" "Their name is Boynton. Mother, married son, his wife, one younger son and two younger daughters."
Dr. Gerard murmured: "La famille Boynton sees the world."
"Yes, but there's something odd about the way they're seeing it. They never speak to anyone else. And none of them can do anything unless the old woman says so!"
"She is of the matriarchal type," said Gerard thoughtfully.
"She's a complete tyrant, I think," said Sarah.
Dr. Gerard shrugged his shoulders and remarked that the American woman ruled the earth-that was well known.
"Yes, but it's more than just that." Sarah was persistent. "She's- Oh, she's got them all so, so cowed-so positively under her thumb-that it's, it's indecent!"
"To have too much power is bad for women," Gerard agreed, with sudden gravity. He shook his head. "It is difficult for a woman not to abuse power." He shot a quick sideways glance at Sarah. She was watching the Boynton family-or rather she was watching one particular member of it. Dr. Gerard smiled a quick comprehending Gallic smile. Ah! so it was like that, was it?
He murmured tentatively: "You have spoken with them-yes?"
"Yes-at least with one of them."
"The young man-the younger son?"
"Yes. On the train coming here from Kantara. He was standing in the corridor. I spoke to him." There was no self-consciousness in Sarah's manner. There was, indeed, no self-consciousness in her attitude to life. She was interested in humanity and was of a friendly though impatient disposition.
"What made you speak to him?" asked Gerard.
Sarah shrugged her shoulders. "Why not? I often speak to people traveling. I'm interested in people-in what they do and think and feel."
"You put them under the microscope, that is to say!"
"I suppose you might call it that," the girl admitted.
"And what were your impressions in this case?"
"Well"-she hesitated-"it was rather odd. . . . To begin with, the boy flushed right up to the roots of his hair."
"Is that so remarkable?" asked Gerard dryly.
Sarah laughed. "You mean that he thought I was a shameless hussy making advances to him? Oh, no, I don't think he thought that. Men can always tell, can't they?"
She gave him a frank, questioning glance. Dr. Gerard nodded his head.
"I got the impression," said Sarah, speaking slowly and frowning a little, "that he was-how shall I put it?-both excited and appalled. Excited out of all proportion-and quite absurdly apprehensive at the same time. Now that's odd, isn't it, because I've always found Americans unusually self-possessed. An American boy of twenty, say, has infinitely more knowledge of the world and far more savoir-faire than an English boy of the same age. And this boy must be over twenty."
"About twenty-three or four, I should say."
"As much as that?" "I should think so."
"Yes . . . perhaps you're right . . . only, somehow, he seems very young. . . ."
"Maladjustment mentally. The 'child' factor persists."
"Then I am right? I mean, there is something not quite normal about him?"
Dr. Gerard shrugged his shoulders, smiling a little at her earnestness. "My dear young lady, are any of us quite normal? But I grant you that there is probably a neurosis of some kind."
"Connected with that horrible old woman, I'm sure!"
"You seem to dislike her very much," said Gerard, looking at her curiously.
"I do. She's got a-oh, a malevolent eye!"
Gerard murmured: "So have many mothers when their sons are attracted to fascinating young ladies!"
Sarah shrugged an impatient shoulder. Frenchmen were all alike, she thought, obsessed by sex! Though, of course, as a conscientious psychologist she herself was bound to admit that there was always an underlying basis of sex to most phenomena. Sarah's thoughts ran along a familiar psychological track. She came out of her meditations with a start. Raymond Boynton was crossing the room to the center table. He selected a magazine. As he passed her chair on his return journey she looked up at him and spoke: "Have you been busy sightseeing today?"
She selected her words at random; her real interest was to see how they would be received.
Raymond half stopped, flushed, shied like a nervous horse and his eyes went apprehensively to the center of his family group. He muttered: "Oh-oh, yes-why, yes, certainly. I-" Then, as suddenly as though he had received the prick of a spur, he hurried back to his family, holding out the magazine.
The grotesque Buddha-like figure held out a fat hand for it, but as she took it her eyes, Dr. Gerard noticed, were on the boy's face. She gave a grunt, certainly no audible thanks. The position of her head shifted very slightly. The doctor saw that she was now looking hard at Sarah. Her face was quite impassive, it had no expression in it. Impossible to tell what was passing in the woman's mind.
Sarah looked at her watch and uttered an exclamation. "It's much later than I thought." She got up. "Thank you so much. Dr. Gerard, for standing me coffee. I must write some letters now."
He rose and took her hand.
"We shall meet again, I hope," he said.
"Oh, yes! Perhaps you will come to Petra?"
"I shall certainly try to do so."
Sarah smiled at him and turned away. Her way out of the room led her past the Boynton family.
Dr. Gerard, watching, saw Mrs. Boynton's gaze shift to her son's face. He saw the boy's eyes meet hers. As Sarah passed, Raymond Boynton half turned his head-not towards her but away from her. . . . It was a slow unwilling motion and conveyed the idea that old Mrs. Boynton had pulled an invisible string.
Sarah King noticed the avoidance, and was young enough and human enough to be annoyed by it. They had had such a friendly talk together in the swaying corridor of the Wagon-Lit. They had compared notes on Egypt, had laughedhow a camel man, when he had started hopefully and impudently, "You English lady or American?" had received the answer: "No, Chinese," and her pleasure in seeing the man's complete bewilderment as he stared at her. The boy had been, she thought, like a nice eager schoolboy-there had been, perhaps, something almost pathetic about his eagerness. And now for no reason at all, he was shy, boorish-positively rude.
"I shan't take any more trouble with him," said Sarah indignantly. For Sarah, without being unduly conceited, had a fairly good opinion of herself. She knew herself to be definitely attractive to the opposite sex, and she was not one to take a snubbing lying down! She had been, perhaps, a shade over-friendly to this boy because, for some obscure reason, she had felt sorry for him.
But now, it was apparent, he was merely a rude, stuck-up, boorish young American! Instead of writing the letters she had mentioned, Sarah King sat down in front of her dressing-table, combed the hair back from her forehead, looked into a pair of troubled hazel eyes in the glass, and took stock of her situation in life.
She had just passed through a difficult emotional crisis. A month ago she had broken off her engagement to a young doctor some four years her senior. They had been very much attracted to each other, but had been too much alike in temperament. Disagreements and quarrels had been of common occurrence. Sarah was of too imperious a temperament herself to brook a calm assertion of autocracy.
Like many high-spirited women, Sarah believed herself to admire strength. She had always told herself that she wanted to be mastered. When she met a man capable of mastering her she found that she did not like it at all! To break off her engagement had cost her a good deal of heart burning, but she was clear-sighted enough to realize that mere mutual attraction was not a sufficient basis on which to build a lifetime of happiness. She had treated herself deliberately to an interesting holiday abroad in order to help on forgetfulness before she went back to start working in earnest.
Sarah's thoughts came back from the past to the present.
"I wonder," she thought, "if Dr. Gerard will let me talk to him about his work? He's done such marvelous work. If only he'll take me seriously . . . Perhaps-if he comes to Petra-" Then she thought again of the strange, boorish young American.
She had no doubt that it was the presence of his family which had caused him to react in such a peculiar manner, but she felt slightly scornful of him, nevertheless. To be under the thumb of one's family like that-it was really rather ridiculous-especially for a man! And yet . . .
A queer feeling passed over her. Surely there was something a little odd about it all?
She said suddenly out loud: "That boy wants rescuing! I'm going to see to it!"
3
When Sarah had left the lounge Dr. Gerard sat where he was for some minutes. Then he walked over to the table, picked up the latest number of Le Matin and strolled with it to a chair a few yards away from the Boynton family. His curiosity was aroused.
He had at first been amused by the English girl's interest in this American family, shrewdly diagnosing that it was inspired by interest in one particular member of the group. But now something out of the ordinary about this family party awakenedin him the deeper, more impartial interest of the scientist. He sensed that there was something here of definite psychological interest.
Very discreetly, under the cover of his paper, he took stock of them. First, the boy in whom that attractive English girl took such a decided interest. Yes, thought Gerard, definitely the type to appeal to her temperamentally. Sarah King had strength-she possessed well-balanced nerves, cool wits and a resolute will. Dr. Gerard judged the young man to be sensitive, perceptive, diffident and intensely suggestible. He noted with a physician's eye the obvious fact that the boy was at the moment in a state of high nervous tension. Dr. Gerard wondered why. He was puzzled. Why should a young man whose physical health was obviously good, who was abroad ostensibly enjoying himself, be in such a condition that a nervous breakdown was imminent?
The doctor turned his attention to the other members of the party. The girl with the chestnut hair was obviously Raymond's sister. They were of the same racial type, small-boned, well-shaped, aristocratic-looking. They had the same slender, well-formed hands, the same clean line of jaw, and the same poise of the head on a long slender neck. And the girl, too, was nervous. . . . She made slight involuntary nervous movements, her eyes were deeply shadowed underneath and over-bright. Her voice, when she spoke, was too quick and a shade breathless. She was watchful-alert-unable to relax.
"And she is afraid, too," decided Dr. Gerard. "Yes, she is afraid!"
He overheard scraps of conversation-a very ordinary normal conversation.
"We might go to Solomon's Stables."
"Would that be too much for Mother?"
"The Weeping Wall in the morning?"
"The Temple, of course-the Mosque of Omar they call it. I wonder why?"
"Because it's been made into a Moslem mosque, of course, Lennox."
Ordinary, commonplace tourists' talk. And yet, somehow, Dr. Gerard felt a queer conviction that these overheard scraps of dialogue were all singularly unreal. They were a mask-a cover for something that surged and eddied underneath-something too deep and formless for words . . . .
Again he shot a covert glance from behind the shelter of Le Matin.
Lennox? That was the elder brother. The same family likeness could be traced, but there was a difference. Lennox was not so highly strung; he was, Gerard decided, of a less nervous temperament. But about him, no, there seemed something odd. There was no sign of muscular tension about him as there was about the other two. He sat relaxed, limp. Puzzling, searching among memories of patients he had seen sitting like that in hospital wards, Gerard thought: "He is exhausted-yes, exhausted with suffering. That look in the eyes-the look you see in a wounded dog or a sick horse-dumb bestial endurance. . . . It is odd, that. . . . Physically there seems nothing wrong with him. . . . Yet there is no doubt that lately he has been through much suffering-mental suffering. Now he no longer suffers-he endures dumbly-waiting, I think, for the blow to fall. . . . What blow? Am I fancying all this? No, the man is waiting for something, for the end to come. So cancer patients lie and wait, thankful that an anodyne dulls the pain a little. . . ."
Lennox Boynton got up and retrieved a ball of wool that the old lady had dropped.
"Here you are. Mother." "Thank you."
What was she knitting, this monumental, impassive old woman? Something thick and coarse. Gerard thought: "Mittens for inhabitants of a workhouse!" and smiled at his own fantasy.
He turned his attention to the youngest member of the party-the girl with the golden red hair. She was, perhaps, seventeen. Her skin had the exquisite clearness that often goes with red hair. Although over-thin, it was a beautiful face. She was sitting smiling to herself-smiling into space. There was something a little curious about that smile. It was so far removed from the Solomon Hotel, from Jerusalem. . . . It reminded Dr. Gerard of something . . . Presently it came to him in a flash. It was the strange unearthly smile that lifts the lips of the Maidens in the Acropolis at Athens-something remote and lovely and a little inhuman. . . . The magic of the smile, her exquisite stillness, gave him a little pang.
And then with a shock, Dr. Gerard noticed her hands. They were concealed from the group around her by the table, but he could see them clearly from where he sat. In the shelter of her lap they were picking-picking-tearing a delicate handkerchief into tiny shreds.
It gave him a horrible shock.
The aloof remote smile-the still body-and the busy destructive hands . . .
4
There was a slow asthmatic wheezing cough-then the monumental knitting woman spoke.
"Ginevra, you're tired; you'd better go to bed."
The girl started; her fingers stopped their mechanical action.
"I'm not tired. Mother."
Gerard recognized appreciatively the musical quality of her voice. It had the sweet singing quality that lends enchantment to the most commonplace utterances.
"Yes, you are. I always know. I don't think you'll be able to do any sightseeing tomorrow."
"Oh! But I shall. I'm quite all right."
In a thick hoarse voice, almost a grating voice, her mother said: "No, you're not. You're going to be ill."
"I'm not! I'm not!" The girl began trembling violently.
A soft calm voice said: "I'll come up with you. Jinny." The quiet young woman with wide, thoughtful gray eyes and neatly coiled dark hair rose to her feet.
Old Mrs. Boynton said: "No. Let her go up alone."
The girl cried: "I want Nadine to come!"
"Then of course I will." The young woman moved a step forward.
The old woman said: "The child prefers to go by herself-don't you Jinny?"
There was a pause-a pause of a moment-then Ginevra Boynton said, her voice suddenly flat and dull: "Yes-I'd rather go alone. Thank you, Nadine."
She walked away, a tall angular figure that moved with a surprising grace.
Dr. Gerard lowered his paper and took a full satisfying gaze at old Mrs. Boynton. She was looking after her daughter and her fat face was creased into a peculiar smile. It was a caricature of the lovely unearthly smile that had transformed the girl's face so short a time before. Then the old woman transferred her gaze to Nadine.
The latter had just sat down again. She raised her eyes and met her mother-in-law's glance. Her face was quite imperturbable. The old woman's glance was malicious.
Dr. Gerard thought: "What an absurdity of an old tyrant!"
And then, suddenly, the old woman's eyes were full on him, and he drew in his breath sharply. Small, black, smoldering eyes they were, but something came from them-a power, a definite force, a wave of evil malignancy. Dr. Gerard knew something about the power of personality. He realized that here was no spoilt tyrannical invalid indulging petty whims. This old woman was a definite force. In the malignancy of her glare he felt a resemblance to the effect produced by a cobra. Mrs. Boynton might be old, infirm, a prey to disease, but she was not powerless.
She was a woman who knew the meaning of power, who recognized a lifetime of power and who had never once doubted her own force. Dr. Gerard had once met a woman who performed a most dangerous and spectacular act with tigers. The great slinking brutes had crawled to their places and performed their degrading and humiliating tricks. Their eyes and subdued snarls told of hatred, bitter fanatical hatred, but they had obeyed, cringed. That had been a young woman, a woman with an arrogant dark beauty, but the look had been the same.
"Une dompteuse!" said Dr. Gerard to himself. And he understood now what that undercurrent to the harmless family talk had been. It was hatred-a dark eddying stream of hatred.
He thought: "How fanciful and absurd most people would think me! Here is a commonplace devoted American family reveling in Palestine-and I weave a story of black magic round it!"
Then he looked with interest at the quiet young woman who was called Nadine. There was a wedding ring on her left hand, and as he watched her, he saw her give one swift betraying glance at the fair-haired, loose-limbed Lennox. He knew, then . . . They were man and wife, those two. But it was a mother's glance rather than a wife's-a true mother's glance-protecting, anxious. And he knew something more. He knew that out of that group, Nadine Boynton alone was unaffected by her mother-in-law's spell. She may have disliked the old woman, but she was not afraid of her. The power did not touch her.
She was unhappy, deeply concerned about her husband, but she was free.
Dr. Gerard said to himself: "All this is very interesting."
5
INTO THESE DARK imaginings a breath of the commonplace came with almost ludicrous effect.
A man came into the lounge, caught sight of the Boyntons and came across to them.
He was a pleasant middle-aged American of a strictly conventional type. He was carefully dressed, with a long, clean-shaven face and he had a slow, pleasant, somewhat monotonous voice.
"I was looking around for you all," he said. Meticulously he shook hands with
